all right hello
everyone welcome to another waking from
the meaning crisis discord
q a our guest today is mark vernon he's
a practicing psychologist
with a history of of physics and a
philosophy a phd on plato
and he's an author of a great many books
the most recent
being the secret history of christianity
welcome mark thank you so much for being
here today
so much for inviting me along and
picking up on the conversation
which it's really great i
feel that you know that are interested
in these things it's lovely to be here
well i'd like to come to so i'd like to
come to the the secret history of
christianity but maybe what i what i'm
first interested in
is so you you've written a lot of books
and you used to be a
a christian priest and then you wrote a
book about
being how to be an agnostic and now
you've written a book
about again when you're back with the
christian
faith so i'm i'm curious as to that
journey
what brought you can you tell us a
little bit about the journey from priest
to agnostic back to believing christian
again
well i underlying
um continuity there is an interest
in inner life
and you know you can see in
explicit spiritual ways explicitly
theistic ways
the idea that the kind of empirical the
material
um it just kind of well certainly just
one dimension if not
a surface reflection of deeper things
i got into the church as a clergy person
in the anglican church
and um most because i didn't really have
the imagination i think to think
otherwise
um i come from a church family
i as it were i enjoyed theology a lot
and i then found off as a
priest in a parish i kind of had a
crisis
i realized that um
of entity unto itself and it works for
many people
um it doesn't work for increasing
numbers of people it seems
certainly in this country um and i
realized it didn't really work for me
um it's life didn't actually
be really find that inner life that i
was looking for
at the time when i left i was left i did
it what they call accuracy which is
bob um i had a crisis that was both
intellectual and personal and i got very
lonely
and in respect can see now i had a sort
of slow
and breakdown of in this
job that i thought was going to be
but left me in a meaning crisis and
um so i left and um first i thought that
i was leaving
being the fresh air of the enlightened
that had seen through
suspicious nonsense that is guaranteed
not all of religion
but i well two things happened one was i
would never quite put down the
aesthetics
things so you know i'd walk into a
cathedral and
it would um it would just not seem
adequate to say
something like you know these buildings
put up
by the excesses of human folly and
fantasy you know they didn't
feel like they were just folly and
fantastic if
things just don't really last thousands
of years i think if they're just
following
um and then also um
in pursuing a kind of uh where am i
gonna find meaning now
i ended up doing a hd on potato
and um that left me very
um by the figure of socrates
can i interrupt for a second we're
getting a bit of choppiness uh
from you i don't know if you can adjust
your mic or
uh maybe move closer to it
um yes if i if i if i
maybe just move a bit closer to it i
hope that might make a difference but do
interject again if
just um that's sounding a bit better now
i think it's it's sounding better um
yeah so i um i did this phd on plato and
um i in retrospect doing the phd i don't
think
really helped me understand what plato
was really driving at
um but i did get very enamored with the
figure of socrates
this idea that the one thing he knew all
was that nothing for sure
um and that made me interested in
agnosticism
um and hence that you mentioned there
and diagnosis don't mean kind of
whatever
i don't know and it doesn't matter i
don't really care
but much more how the edges of what we
know
um absolute most important parts of
what we do and don't know and because
then we might step into
a much wider and bigger world and i
think that's what socrates was really on
about
um so um
there's still a kind of even in my
agnosticism as it were it's still driven
by
interest in inner life and what is
missing
um from empirical scientific perception
um and i've ended up writing this book
on christianity
i feel a bit nervous about being called
a christian because that means
so many things to so many different
people and um
usually it's meant to kind of put you in
a box um
and i i ended up reading this chap owen
barfield
who and was one of the inklings and
great friend of c.s lewis and j.r
tolkien
and um he finally made help me make
sense
thought first of all of plato and then
also
hence a sense of the christian tradition
i felt much more aligned and now
i could go on about that at great length
but um that's something about the kind
of
lecture journey at least so
you you eventually came to came across
john verveigh
how did so how did you come to know
john's work and
how does it intersect with your own
yeah well i'm i i have i'm
interested in a number of people online
who are pursuing these questions of
meaning
and john's long series on the meaning
crisis
interesting for its own sake and to run
through all that
um but then i was really surprised when
he had at least one half
episode on owen barfield there's very
few people
oh barfield let alone want to talk about
him um
so i emailed him john and said you know
it was a great
joy to go and barfield disgust um if you
don't mind me saying so i'm not sure
um you completely got it right but
nonetheless
really important stuff here um and i
said i've written a book
that tells the story of christianity
using barfield's insights
which is a secret history of
christianity um and he was very
interested in that and so we had the
first conversation which was probably
around barfield
and then i'm now also involved in a
research project based at cambridge
university
also a think tank called perspective
and it's a project looking at what
spiritual intelligence might be
and particularly as distinct from say
artificial intelligence
and so john was interested in that as
well and i'm very interested in his
um or e cognitive science reaching
out in much more expansive directions
the second conversation we have was
aimed around uh spiritual intelligence
and so your your no so your secret
history i mean it sounds like a
conspiratorial type book just from the
title but but it but it's not really
right
you're you're talking about an approach
to to studying
christianity is that that right yes so
it's secret as
in um not immediately self-evident
um and it comes from jesus actually
jesus talked about the secrets of the
kingdom
and i think what he really was meaning
there is that what he stood for
was cultivation of
a very different perception of life and
what it was all about
um and perception of life that requires
a
shift of consciousness um and
when that shift of consciousness happens
either in disease or
and maybe in larger steps and realize
that it was there all along
and but it was kind of hidden like a
secret treasure as a beneath your feet
and so that's what i mean by the time
but
i wanted it to have a slight sense of
intrigue because i think you need to
have that sense of
am i going to discover something i
didn't even really suspect
get that shift of consciousness if you
think it's going to be just the kind of
rearrangement of what you know already
that shifted consciousness will never
happen um but
it has got these other connotations um
as well which i don't know whether that
puts people off or not but anyway i took
the gamble
so we we have uh we've got a question
from
from stroon who's uh who's i'm gonna
read
his audio's choppy so i'm gonna read it
uh how does plato's views and knowledge
relate to his views on virtue
and how does that position relate to the
overall value of the platonic dialogues
given that plato thought you could only
have real knowledge of what was eternal
and unchanging
yes so um this is uh
referring to one of the attempts to
summarize
any well even socrates origin virtue
the historical socrates perhaps wondered
about this too
um but um plato certainly talks about
this
and what did the idea is that you only
really know what you resonate with um
scientific knowledge um actually a
rather
um verified
exceptional kind of knowledge in that it
seems to be objective
um so who you are in principle
doesn't matter when it comes to
scientific knowledge is it where
anyone can look at the second law of
motion
and in principle understand it i mean
just in parenthesis my first degree was
actually a physic
and i realized now that degree in
physics is essentially an initiation
process to see whether you can really
speak
physics and so in fact you have to
change
quite a lot to fix to have to
get a hang of abstract um objective
mathematical approaches
to um by being reality
oh actually i think the way you have to
be able to resonate
reality even as a scientist really to be
a good scientist
um but nonetheless plato was very clear
that
um when you really know what and felt
or intuitive or um participative
connection with so if reality
up to the chase that rather simply if
reality
is the base goods beautiful and true
and have at least something of what's
good what's beautiful and true in you
really know it directly and otherwise no
amount of telling
will persuade you i think it's
indifferent or maybe even think it's bad
um
so you have to work on yourself to
cultivate the capacity
be what's good and true and which the
shorthand word for would be the virtue
um so virtues are kind of personal
qualities or characteristics
um that become part of who you are um
and you know i think there's no nothing
very amazing about this you know if you
fall in love with someone
that lovingly or to them they act
lovingly was you
he sides of them that perhaps even no
one else see
and so we know i think even in our
everyday experience that
the person we are and does open or close
what we can perceive and appreciate and
see in life
and so plato was onto that
as the kind of foundation for all our
knowing and the only big knowing
in life that really makes a difference
in life
i think that he wrote his dialogues um
cultivate that sense of knowing though
they are dialogues
um they're very different kinds of
dialogues you know sometimes it's almost
like a lecture from socrates
sometimes it's almost like a talk from
someone else sometimes it's much more
like genuine encounters
and sometimes the framing seems odd it's
to kind of throw you in a
state of unknowing to me you really
grapple with what's being said
and but a key thread that runs through
that is
are you yourself um being invited to
change
as you eat these dialogues i think
plato wanted to try and um replicate
experience of eating socrates in the
flesh and so that
even now we can appreciate something
well
and you mentioned that and you said this
to john as well that
you didn't quite get plato even when you
were doing an entire phd on it but then
barfield
opened plato up for you wha what were
you missing
and what what what that that you now
know and that you now apply when you
read
plato yeah so the heart of it i guess
would be that consciousness evolves
and by which our field meant that it
our experience of being alive and our
perceptions what seems
um self-evident to us and what things
um questionable dramatically shifts
over time and whilst
um plato and the other ancient greek
philosophers
um i think shared many aspects of our
own conscious
um in particular they thought that um
it's good for the individual ask
question which
hasn't always been the case in human
history at all um but that was beginning
to become a sort of uh
exactly mainstream but a an acceptable
idea
and that's i think why philosophy is we
think of it was born
at that time um
there's things which are very different
in plato still
and barfield got this words he realized
that words
with meaning very substantially and so
he said the first thing you need to do
when you read plato is to unthink what
you think you know
by say words like theory because for
plato theory
doesn't mean an abstract idea that you
put to the empirical test
it primarily means it almost means a
journey you go on
where you encounter a new horizon and
see whether you can
step over that horizon in the world
um and so you have to
all the key words in plato you have to
um
to one side what you think they mean and
then try and work
on your own consciously to um
appreciate what he meant back then and
then
it really starts to open up particularly
if you just treat it as
best of rational argument analyze
you don't really get anywhere for him um
and
you might even be altered out of that
perception by realizing that plato
didn't even have the word analysis
was no such word in plato's time that's
how profound
difference is for all that plato can
also seem accessible
so so we've talked about here on the
discord about forming a reading group
of going through plato's uh dialogues
and sort of
acting them out you know having
different people play the different
parts
but you know for the lay person so for
for us who
you know those of us who aren't plato
scholars how would you recommend we
approach
those books without you know an in-depth
knowledge of
what each of the words means in the
history of the words or or are we just
at a deficit
without doing a fair amount of
background research
um but i think it's you can kind of
start with
um uh one particular dialogue
um i mean a good one to start with i
think is symposium
um because uh erotic love
and subjects the conversations as um
still means more or less the same thing
to us at one level
at relationships and being attracted
to physical bodies other people um but
if you let yourself
go with what they also seem to imply
in the dialogue about eros actually it's
their passion
it connects us with um the most dynamic
and compelling aspects of reality as a
whole
not just another person and then you can
start to
get a feel for what dialogue is trying
to really break open for you
through this common experience of erotic
love if you start with one like that
you know i think you can um
not to make headway and then build from
there in a way
but it's also really important i think
that kind of translation
um preferably one with a good um
introductory essay that's aware that
nato was trying to do more than just
anglo-american philosophy
um you know and and sometimes actually
older translations are better so like
shelly the romantic poet
um did a translation of plato's
symposium um and
language is a bit strange because it is
older but in a way that's
no really because it just you do that
extra bit of work
rather than thinking there's aristotle
i've got that i'm in a rational way
when i you know wants some
recommendations on
a particular translations then i can
certainly offer that
um also you know read read barfield um
or indeed
you know if i may say so i've got a
couple of chapters precisely on this
i think the ancient really about in my
own book i really try and
owe a sense of what they're about as
well as to discuss them with
birds as well we'll probably take you up
on that as we're
as we're starting up our our book club
um
good goodbye q has a question
oh thank you thank you um i was
wondering if you would be able to
oh explain your best uh
to define nothing as if as when plato
says uh
the only thing he knows is he knows
nothing or
some translation of that and then
if if able to extrapolate on your
ex explanation of nothing uh to
try to help explain the value of getting
to know
nothing yeah thank you
um yeah so um
maybe qualify my very slightly you pick
me up on my direct quote i think um
though um that he knew nothing before um
the um so a closer sense of things
because
the opinion we do know some things know
how to step out of the house in the
morning
and how to say hello to our neighbor um
when you start to ask what's going on
with those encounters do you think that
they're to do with friendship
one of his dialogues is on friendship
you start to ask what friendship's
really about
and quite quickly you start to realize
that perhaps the assumptions you were
working
with don't hold in all situations or
you know maybe it's actually quite hard
to pin down the essence of friendship
um and why that's important
to you it's partly a question of
humility
don't forget he lives in this period of
athenian democracy which he saw
really going basically wrong um
he lived through the peloponnesian war
um
iteration on conflict with martins
and it was eventually the undoing of
athens actually
so he lived for a time of kind of
athenian crisis
and um displaying the democracy
or problems he felt are more than just
athens in particular it requires a
certain kind of education
um and education that's really involved
it's not just how to win an
argument in the hall courts if it would
show you that
how to have some modesty um about what
we do and don't know
um so um he wanted to
cultivate that for kind of practical but
there's a spiritual side to it or a
metaphysical like to it as well because
um he realized that um this aporia
as he put it this kind of moment when
you start to
realize that what you thought you knew
is
actually much harder to pin down or to
appreciate
um you'd assumed that
he felt i think and plato certainly felt
is actually the
of life itself um so
in in contact with that um i mean the
word that sometimes uses that kind of
noetic
sense and so it's beyond a propositional
sense of things
um moving towards that which seems
beyond just straightforward propositions
um and you might know much clearly
because you're drawn to it because it
it shows a certain kind of beauty the
words we use now would be the sublime or
the wonderful
um you feel um it's it's
it's vitality um but you don't want to
pin it down too much because
otherwise you start curtailing that
vitality and curtailing that
expansiveness and so knowing nothing
i mean maybe um it's a bit like the
buddhist i think it's quite like the
buddhist conception of emptiness
if emptiness doesn't just mean a kind of
nihilistic void
it actually means the potential from
which everything might emerge um
or i mean plato wasn't a theist in our
sense there was no
sense of monotheism at the time but
platonism certainly became very
important in
sexualizing monotheism and especially in
this sense that um
vine is understandable to us to a degree
but we constantly have to remember that
we're trying to talk about something or
know something appreciate something live
by something that
ultimately is beyond us this is actually
the source of our life and our vitality
in some way
um yeah so again this is his kind of
agnosticism
actually opening up on life rather than
um either i don't care or just kind of
closing it down
did you have a follow-up uh goodbye q
um i'm not sure how to articulate it but
i'd like to try and thank you for that
forget that response so
there's something again i'm trying to
articulate this as i
intend uh there's a difference
between knowing nothing
and not knowing anything
yeah yeah so um
maybe this is the sense in which it
meant it um
i don't forget i i think the word for
nothing
i think that came in later english so
nothing as we
um you know vacuum the void etc
um i don't think they back then so he
couldn't have meant it in that sense
um um what
you know to tell the story you know the
famous story that he tells in the
apologies another good dialogue to read
as a starter
is um friend of his went to the delphic
oracle
and apollo the god through the delphic
oracle told him that no one's wiser than
socrates
and he immediately knew that
to understand an oracle you need to
question um oracles don't just
spoon feed you they make you wrestle
with truth
and the gods want to share their
insights with you which
to change underground capable of
receiving it
but he decides that he's going to go
around and find someone wiser than
athens to prove the oracle wrong and
he claims that he asks the politicians
and realizes that they
really know what they're talking about
they just believe their own rhetoric and
he speaks to the poets and
realizes that they're very good with
words but just that doesn't mean you
know what you're talking
about you still get artisans to make a
pot or a pair of shoes or
something on um but they don't really
mean they know anything else
much and then he realizes why he's wise
is because he's conscious
of the edges of what he doesn't know um
even
as he pursues um awareness of things
so that is that sense that um he meant
it
thank you very much thank you
mark you have a question
yes um mark that's a great name that you
have there
really really appreciate that first name
um
i so there's sort of three concepts here
that stood out to me that you've
mentioned so far
that i find uh kind of fascinating and
so i
uh instead of like a specific question
with a with a definite answer i just
was wondering if you could uh maybe riff
on this a bit and maybe it doesn't fit
together so
you know don't don't worry about sort of
not addressing one of these but
you you made an allusion to the fact
that uh
there's an importance behind aesthetics
that last
right and then you you know so via the
church etc it seems more
real right than something that say
fashion for example
um and then you talked about uh and you
just talked about it again the edges of
our knowledge
allowing us to step into a bigger and
wider world
uh and and and then i was wondering if
that's
if those two concepts in any way are
connected to each other and if they're
connected to this
uh this thing you talked about as eros
as a connection to the dynamic reality
of the world if you could just
like riff on those three and maybe if
they go together or
you know i'd like to get your general
sense because all three of these things
are
are are interesting and and sort of uh
uh
in the sphere of uh discussions we have
here on the uh
on this discord uh server yeah thank you
thank you and uh um let's i'll speak and
then
hit me up um
well um i mean maybe it just adds
another bit
um or impersonally which i haven't
mentioned actually but was
very fundamental um is that um one
things which happened when i the church
was i went into psychotherapy
olly because i needed help um but also
because i did begin to get this sense
that
psychotherapy is closer to ancient
philosophy
and modern philosophy because the whole
point of psychotherapy is that you try
and understand what's going on inside
you
and unlike a behavioral therapy doesn't
really ask you to change it asks you to
manage their
psychotherapy invites you to change
understand things um so
psychotherapy i think is a really
good um analog for ancient
philosophy it's not the only one but
it's a very good one
because um you know in psychotherapy
you know you've got a problem and you
can't you're wrestling with it you can't
seem to resolve it
so it takes you to a kind of edge of
your knowledge which you know because of
comfort or distress or anxiety or
depression whatever it might be
um and the psychotherapist says look
i'll sit with you
and wrestle with you on this and try and
bring
all the insights which i can to bear on
it as well
um and we will stay as much as we can
tolerate
at the edge of your knowledge of
yourself see what
shows up and that in a way i think
to engage the erotic in this broader
sense
because one way it requires a kind of
trust of the
process and maybe even the analyst um
it requires a desire which can be a
struggle can be a passion in
you know the very difficult sense as
well
to own more of yourself um
and um i think it requires imagination
as well
um i think imagination is perhaps
word that we would use now um to uh
capture some of this sense that um
insights
um or awareness can come from places
that we don't fully
understand or maybe don't even
understand at all you know be that
dreams
and be that intuitions and be that
a strange thing happens today be that an
encounter that was
difficult or compelling in some way
and and imaginatively to engage with
all these things um comes a pathway to
understanding more about ourselves and
then understanding more about those
around us and the world
as well and these things last
because um they have the capacity
so these things you i think truth are
the truth of these things
not necessarily truth as in doctrinal
truth
truths as in um this feels like
uh reality is expanding for me and
picking me somewhere um
because they last because they become
creative because
they do offer more meaning um and you
know that's partly because
things which were so pressing before
ease
don't get resolved completely but they
certainly ease
and you start to appreciate more of life
and you feel
fuller you feel richer um as the
romantics put it
like coleridge
field was very very indebted like
they made this distinction between
france's imagination and they said
fantasy is
playful and it might be witty but it
just comes and goes
and it makes you laugh one day and then
just being unmoved the next
there's something that is genuinely
imaginative um
really lasts and it's something to build
on it feels like a source of life
and takes you into new worlds a new
appreciation of things
and so you know a deep aesthetic um
can do that if you go into a
thousand-year-old cathedral here in
london
um it will make you feel there's
something going on here even though
parts of it
as in years ago has lasted and it's
lasted for a reason
i think because it's actually something
um
that transcends those thousand years and
that is
closer something more eternal
in reality in the sense of timeless
wow that was um that was really
interesting uh what you came out with
there uh
i yeah this uh
this uh combines quite nicely with a
bunch of stuff i've been
uh pondering and we've been discussing
uh on the
discord server in general and
just to i mean i guess i guess the only
sort of missing piece for me because all
of this looks really good
is uh you know so there's two sort of
issues
around around getting that sense right i
mean all these people
you know to your point are sort of
falling away from
from the church or from you know that
sense of i guess it's religio
although maybe i'm misusing john's term
i never quite know
i'll ask him today um and and so
i'm wondering you know is is
do you know do you do you know why we
might be missing the
imagination to re-engage we'll say
using our erotic sense
with our deeper uh past aesthetic
i yeah i think it's because our
consciousness has shifted again
and if a bit in between
times um i'm a transition
i think it began quite a long time ago
probably in the 17th century with
what we call the enlightenment what we
call the reformation scientific
revolution
um our field felt that there were kind
of cycle
human consciousness where um periods of
withdrawal
where women individuals or
collectively in culture and in on
themselves a bit
and in a way only trials
and that has the advantage that it
deepens the sense of yourself
and brings many of the advantages which
we experience in the modern world
has the disadvantage that it can leave
you feeling cut off and lead to a
meaning crisis
and but um michael carries on and
eventually things like psychotherapy
emerge
and that enable us to reconnect i think
some practices you know which john in
his own journey has been very naturally
led
towards and realizing that a rational
analysis which
from the scientific age tells us should
be able to deliver everything
he's in life doesn't in fact
and so in the search and struggle things
like practices start to
pop up or as he's getting onto as well
dialogue
and which in a dialogue well actually
the two that matters is
the third thing that comes in when
people are conversing it's that sense oh
my goodness
that was wonderful um we made that
connection i didn't think i was going to
say that
um or you feel you're moving towards a
horizon and something's opening up
and we just haven't really trusted these
ways very much in recent
years and centuries kept alive i think
in things like the romantic
but unfortunately christianity
only i know you know which i guess is a
sort of western christianity
um has lost tr lost touch with with what
would have been called the mystical
tradition the visionary
referring back to my secret in the title
of my book
um felt it needs to be scientific
um or conversely it's very elevated
at the kind of experience the kind of
emotional high
um you know and they kind of deliver
something on a sunday morning but by
sunday afternoon it started to run dry a
bit
you have to go back again and top up and
eventually you get
a bit fed up of topping up and you think
well maybe there's nothing in it
um christianity in the west i think has
very largely lost this sense that you're
supposed to change
you know that it makes you submit late
to the figure of jesus
as if jesus has done all the work and i
think that's a fundamental mistake
um and so people are falling away from
it and
why why wouldn't they because it's not
really
delivering on its promise
yeah that uh that makes a lot of sense i
mean basically
the summarize uh you know let me know if
i've got this right
it's something like uh
too much uh the so the church has
focused too much
on on procedure and submission
and not enough on uh
personal transformation and engagement
yeah yeah i mean it's complicated
because um
at least a lot of what church is is
really valuable um and
good so certainly in this country the
church of england
you know it's quite it's very heavily
associated with social work and
um defending people that um
don't get a voice and so on uh correct
concerns of justice
um you know that's obviously a good
thing posted and what i'm doing
the risk is that leaving the park text
me please takes away from the personal
transformation and the point is that to
be a leader
in personal transformation you have to
be transforming yourself
um and so if your priesthood and
thinks that its main task is pastoral
care
that may be a very good thing but it may
mean that
they aren't changing themselves and they
won't
emit that spirit and they won't know how
to guide people
um whereas you know the contrast to me
is very much with psychotherapy where
you have to go for your own therapy you
have to be
what's the process of change be a good
psychotherapist
um and so that personal transformation
and then you know collective as well
um insofar as it ripples out central
so it i think that that's
what mistaken about what delivers my
knowledge but also
it's lost the practice in a way and
these practices aren't
easy to regain because they are you know
they're felt ills really
um it's not like um
just reading a book and getting it um
you have to go on the journey
and you make mistakes and it's struggle
and you think
it's going to be a failure and because
this is not just about extending what
you know already
about something you emerging um and so
you have to have people around
who can say look stick with it um
i know you don't trust i know this is
really even quite painful
um but go for it you know and the
and the buddhists know this um you know
certainly the the way the buddhist
practice is coming into the west it's a
major selling point
they have when it's not just how to kind
of do a bit of mindfulness to help you
stay at work
there's that side of it but you know a
serious buddhist practice
knows this and that's why it makes you
sit on the cushion and it hurts
because they know that something's on
the other side
you mentioned that uh you know for
example the ancient athenians spent
40 to 50 50 of their day on various
rituals and participatory religious
actions
and just mention christians getting away
from that
what ecology of practices do you follow
yeah i mean it's a good question and um
a very largely
the moment anyway around two areas one
is the psychotherapy practice
that's um about
thirds of my week um so that means being
with people and then it means also doing
the personal work
and whether that be provision as it's
called with other therapists
i'm being thinking about what's going on
my own personal practice which you know
paul d is around meditation
um but also am i i i'm quite
a believer in um
thinking as well thinking in the service
of
experienced phillip experience and so
i'm
[Music]
actually at the moment a big online
project for me is um
dante's divine comedy so the divine
comedy is 700
years old this year and um the huge
amount written about the divine comedy
but
eventually missing is the divine comedy
as a spiritual practice
as a spiritually transformative text i'm
doing a
canto by kanto podcasting on the divine
comedy
and to be alert to what's going on for
dante
and of course that means i have to be
alert in myself to
be what's going on with minds insofar as
i can
and so in christian circles that would
be called lectio divina
i'm a kind of contemplative body of text
into in a felt sense of what's being
communicated
um i'm also a huge fan of william blake
i live in south london and blake
and the road angels on peckham rye which
is just
for me and i'm very fascinated by that i
think we feel that blake
um he had visions he had strange
experiences
life um but he didn't just sort of as it
were
enjoy the trip but enormously hard
make sense of that both in english and
in
words in poetry and because i think he
you realize that you have to
take that into yourself be able to make
something of it be able to
participate in otherwise is due an odd
experience or a strange vision
um and so blake has become extremely
important
to me actually as i wrestle with him you
know he's really is quite hard to
understand beyond hating the better
known poems
um but i think he deliberately makes you
struggle
because in the struggle um something
starts to show up
and lectio divina is one of the
practices we've we've been implementing
here we're based on john's uh
john's model uh so and blake has
actually come up
in uh some of our lectio divination mark
who just asked a question
it's a fan of blake and and has brought
that in
so we're your your your divine comedy
podcast is that on your youtube channel
yes yes so it's on the youtube and then
it's a buzz sprout
um audio version as well you can find it
on my website
okay i'm sorry great nick you have a
question
uh yeah um i'm also a big fan of blake
so i was happy to hear that uh
crediting of his work um my
question uh revolves around tillich
and if you are familiar with him and uh
if so
how you might view his work in light of
barfield's work
and also how we might see tilik
as kind of uh wrestling with classical
theism
um and if that perhaps could be
considered a kind of
revitalization of classical theism
um and perhaps how it might relate to
platonic and neoplatonic
thought and what they were actually
aiming at as opposed to the kind of uh
perhaps
overly gnostic flavor that's often
credited
uh to them
yeah i mean the first thing i should say
is i don't actually know a huge amount
about tilik beyond
headline occasionally it's like ground
of being myself and so on and
appreciation that comes out of
existentialism
existentialism um so if i say
a couple of things then you can tell me
whether they're actually
helpful or not because they may just not
be um i think that
um barfield was suspicious of
existentialism
um and i think the reason was was
because
um he felt that its premise was that
um we have to
our gift as well our freedom is
something of life and you know our
existence comes before our essence
and um he felt that
that probably only generates those
symptoms of meaning
um where um you know maybe a very
elaborate
apology or philosophy um maybe one that
is full of passion you know full of fear
and trembling and
born and ethically very demanding
um can be forged and but
i think he feared that it just leaves
you ultimately
turning circles on yourself um
and um it was very clear that um
the goal of consciousness is not just to
know the inside of your own psyche and
maybe the inside of
a culture's psyche as he put it the
inside of the whole world
and so i think he was suspected that
actually travel of existentialism
[Music]
to reach out um and to
develop a rich spiritual ecology say
ex world would include a clued angels
and
dude um all sorts of entities and
intelligence
beings which he calls albion and any
thumb
on and all the rest of it um you know
you don't really read that
in public i don't think um and so
yeah i think that's he wouldn't be
against it per se
but he would recognize i think um
theistic existentialism
as an attempt to um advise
way of thinking that could carry
something of
um moreness of life the mystical side um
but um at the end of the day and
barfield and sometimes this is said to
blake actually that
was wrong to call blake and mystic he
was actually a visionary
um he he brought things and he could put
it into him
into words um and um
it wasn't just that kind of
philosophical language which
and very wonderfully at times um
can can convey a kind of dance around
the core mystery
ultimately is a sort of dance around the
core mystery um
and yeah maybe i'll just stop there and
ask whether that actually charms with
anything that you recognize
um yeah so that's interesting i i
i perhaps i don't know if this is on
your end or my end but i
i did not distinctly get the sense from
tilik
as being overly um
uh kind of embedded in an existentialist
framework um i can see it to me it makes
sense that he was
starting there but trying to seemingly
uh break
that that wall uh of the kind of uh
solipsistic
quality of existentialism um
that you you know you are rightfully
criticizing and is
is uh likewise a criticism that i've
i've made as well
um but yeah that's uh
nonetheless nonetheless interesting
would you say in some sense then that
barfield's um
take and perhaps i'm i'm reading this
from
more of c.s lewis's apologetics but that
it had a more
modernist grounding
um just you i'm you know i'm very happy
to hear that about tillick and i'm
happy that
thanks and that might well be right yeah
he wants to do or
sort of starting from where he was at as
it were um
on um on barfield
and lewis had this lifelong argument
um about eason and the imagination
and it as you might expect a lot of
nuance and they're both very very
brilliant
thinkers and individuals um in their own
way
broadly speaking i think you can say
that our field never persuaded lewis
fully but the imagination itself could
be truth-bearing
um it's always felt you've really got to
come up with a good argument
um to know that it's really true um
and so you know and again i i appreciate
that
on your stories um you know can feel
very different to different people but
for me i'm one of those people that
reads bananas because it always feels
they're a bit allegorical
they're a bit illustrated other than say
tolkien
but you feel you absolutely enter um
a complete world to complete cosmos um
and that's because i think talking like
barfield completed the imagination
um and so that was his primary
off and you then have to work hugely
hard to
words even the language in tolkien's
case so it's not without reason at
all the reason is in the service of the
imagination i think louis
always felt that imagination is the
other way around um and so
they're very different way i mean the
way that
that it might even more explicit the bar
field
when he um persuaded about the power of
the imagination
and just what through his philology he
apologized so he he studied words and
how words change meaning so he had kind
of an empirical base for
and but when he worked out sense of
things
then discovered rudolf steiner um
and um chris never begin to understand
why barfi was
interested in kind of um you know i'll
put my hand up and say i'm not complete
or either i get some sense of it now
but um if you the colorful disagreement
over steiner but there was a sort of uh
degree disagreement about the
relationship between and the imagination
and so i think lewis's success in
circles is precisely because he
seems to offer a
sense of christianity um
and in
in the world in a christian culture
which needs rational defense it
is as good as it gets um but
not good enough i don't at the end of
the day it leaves you with this vague
sense that
the argument but really
they life is full in my view
right i i would agree with you there and
i uh appreciate that
that differentiation between uh uh
barfield
and and louis there i i would uh
definitely fall on the side of
barfield um one thing that came to mind
as you were describing
that that difference seems to be almost
this this
uh totally different idea of what the
logos
actually represents with with um
lewis kind of falling on logos as logic
and bar field falling uh towards this
this uh much more
kind of alive or dynamic sense of the
logos
in the creative pursuit itself
uh and how that relates to the imaginary
yeah so um again one way of putting it
you know as a starter at least a bit
more complicated than this
subtle and sophisticated to lewis credit
you know he's immensely i think i
wouldn't want to
deny that for a moment and but as a
starter for 10
um i think lewis had a broadly
scientific understanding of the logos
which is
um that it's objective tool
um that is like
atoms um and structures as it were
throughout the cosmos
um ways of being in a kind of ordered
sense
and so it's rational in that sense as i
think for barfield
um the heart of hogos is actually soul
it's vitality birds have meaning because
they convey
energy spirits and you don't just as
points at things they actually
channel what they're pointing at to you
um you know which is explicitly so in
poetry but even in prose and so the
logos
is um the vitalizing principle
in the cosmos um it's the it's the far
in the equations not just the equations
to einstein's phrase
um and that again that that i think they
they could argue the toss a lot but
there's something about that
difference distinguishes them
right thank you for that um i guess a
final follow-up
might be pulling it back to one of my uh
initial questions here
would be uh how much do you think that
um you know what what barfield was
aiming for there
was present in uh platonic
and neoplatonic thought and was
do you see it as in some way part of
that tradition or a re uh
reconfiguration of it
it's a good question um we look
it's just a thought which i hope
somewhere um
i think that um
oh you know the logos begins in the
western anyway in the rest of written to
just
with heraclitus at the logos and
for heraclitus it was the principle that
altogether
the sense that everything is dynamic
everything's in a bit of flux
into the same river twice and all that
with
a sense of unity that although you can't
step into the same river twice it's
still the same river
and there is something that amidst the
flux holds things all together
and that oneness he called the logos
and so he says you know don't listen to
me listen to the logos he was constantly
pointing towards that sense of
vision and rather than just neat
comments about rivers flowing
um so that gets picked up i think in
plato
um you know um
they had great
faith in words you know plato prunedly
so he was an amazing writer
um which i next
keep on giving um and so
that flux ability is actually in his
dialogues
um you can read them again and they can
look
any different over the course of your
own life
and yet somehow they're all they're
still revolving around
one thing that dialogues might
channel and so that's the power of the
logos i think
later um neoplatonism
they try to knit that in with stoicism
of course
and and also um
the perspective brought by aristotle i i
think that plato and aristotle are so
complimentary rather than
be different and again a huge subject
for discussion but
um and so in particular what happens i
think is that
in stoicism you get this much more
bigger stress on on self-reflection
um and is even really in plato um
it's a sort of deepening of the sense of
the individual that comes in the
hellenistic age
and so that focuses on our relationship
with logos um
and um
you know recently it's called um
spiritual exercises
are very much bringing on that it brings
in a more personal element and then i
think christianity
actually says the logos has become
incarnate in a person that's how strong
the link
is between this divine box that's also
one
um that actually it can be completely
and fully transmitted in we human beings
the task comes not just as it were
writing beautifully about
the logos it has dialogues but becomes
actually eliminating the logos in your
own life
all invited there in that relational
possibility now
um so becomes you know
by up close personal insight outside
across that tradition from heraclitus
it's certainly the greek dutch fathers
who in that way
they're so powerfully influenced by
platonism platinus
right that was wonderful thank you very
much
so in the introduction to your book uh
to into the secret life of christianity
you you talk about knowing uh
that your life springs from god's life
and this truth is yours to be discovered
now
putting aside the specifics of that
claim you talk about that it can be
known directly
not on the basis of someone else else's
report or someone else's authority
or someone else's rhetoric but inwardly
and reliably
now so on that word reliably uh
i i i'm a big proponent of you know
withholding belief in
claims you know absent sufficient
reliable evidence
based on that internal felt experience
how
how do you how do you get to reliable
yep um you you've
uh quite correctly you know draw me up
on my initial
offer in the book and
i think that um
the reliability um comes with the change
of
with and the development of your sense
of self
um and it's it reason why i say direct
is because at the end of the day it does
rest in the sense of yourself
um and um you kind of know it when you
see it it's a bit like
the comment that sometimes made about
music if you've got to ask you'll never
know
um in music to me no you some expression
will help but ultimately you've got to
listen and
get into it and then directly why it's
so powerful
it's that kind of a journey um
i mean one way that this was schematized
i hope this is illuminating it doesn't
just feel like dodging the question
um but one way that this was
traditionally schematized certainly in
the christian tradition was
how various kind of levels of knowing um
and basic level is literal
um and it's not very reliable
is it easily fixed with other claims to
knowledge you know literal truths tend
to conflict
they have very limited scope and the
next level was
allegorical and that you say something
to point to something more than just the
literal in a kind of parallel way
um so if i said um
i'm a tiger literate um because i've got
ginger hair
say um you would know literally that's
not true
if i said no but i'm like a type i think
oh well maybe he's saying he's got a bit
of a fierce temp
temper or something like that so you can
sort of make some sense of that
statement
um if i said no no i'm a tiger
and we'll say for us of course that
would get you to a third level
um which would be the tropological level
in the tradition
uh the shock of me saying no i'm a tiger
if you think oh my goodness i haven't
really understood what on earth he was
saying at all
and he's not just saying he's got a
fierce temper he's saying something else
and then i say maybe in a bit more of a
zen-like way i'm at you think oh
maybe he's saying life one
and one with the tiger because life is
one in some way there's a
deep perception of being in that um
now that um when you glimpse that
that is eyeball knowledge and a reliable
kind of awareness
um but it takes this journey
to it um i think you know when when i
say it's reliable also perhaps i should
qualify it by saying
that um i don't think it's something
that you know all day every day
invariably you'll have our ups and downs
but
when you return to it you realize it's
the same
perception that before and so over time
you begin to trust that it's there even
when you don't see it
and so it's reliable in that sense
so so the reliability isn't necessarily
on the propositional claim but on the
the the participatory claim the
perspectival claim and i thank you i
mean they're great words that john uses
and
i think that's precisely that's it
there's you know i think that would be a
good
that difference yeah the propositions
are good starters for 10.
like doctrines are good starters for ten
like scientific theories kind of
placeholders for a while um but you know
they're gonna
be um inadequate at some point that is
part of their purpose as well
and so you know propositional knowledge
um
is it can do for a time it's a bit like
saying i'm a christian that's what i'm
nervous is saying i'm a christian
i wouldn't want that to be thought as a
kind of literal proposition because
already it means a thousand different
things to a thousand different people
um but you know if i said something like
christian way of seeing things has got
deep resources that
actually i think is one of the best off
ways to
truest things that we can know um
that is uh is
going to annoy people that want
propositional statements that actually
feels much more
rude to me
all right well this has been uh this has
been just a great
discussion and question answer
thank you so much for for coming today
and
and sharing with us and uh yeah great
answers and great questions thank you so
much for everyone
for being here it's uh
yeah thank you you know you're welcome
back anytime
uh you know we'd love to we'd love to
have you back maybe after your next uh
voices with uh with verveiki
oh look thank you too because
this stuff comes alive when you talk
about it um you know you try and make it
live in a book
maybe have some success there but
ultimately it comes alive because it is
shared that is precisely
you know what we're talking about and
you i feel it
and hopefully you can find the right
questions and the right words to
bring it war so i really appreciate what
you're doing
organizing this and i'd be very happy to
put more well thank you so much and
again thank you everyone for being here
we've got uh john coming back on monday
for another uh
q a and a full schedule so everyone if
you could please uh
you know subscribe to our google
calendar it's a it's the pinned post in
the
announcements channel and uh i'll post a
link to our youtube channel so please
subscribe all these
q a's are uploaded to youtube so please
subscribe and like
like the videos especially if you miss
uh uh
if you missed one you could you can
catch up to them there then again thanks
again mark for for being here this was
amazing really appreciate it
yeah thank you so much mark that was
wonderful
yeah thanks mark